Guide to the Teunis G. Bergen and Bergen family collection ARC.006
Brooklyn Historical Society
Teunis G. Bergen and Bergen family collection
1639-1893
Brooklyn Historical Society
Bergen, Teunis G.
Bergen family
Conover family
Cortelyou family
Cortelyou, Peter
Cowenhoven family
Whitman, Walt
Wyckoff family
ARC.006
16.91 Linear Feet in 34 manuscript boxes, one half manuscript box, one shoe box, two oversize folders (OS-34), and 22 flat file folders.
The Teunis G. Bergen and Bergen family collection comprises the papers of Teunis G. Bergen (1806-1881), as well as the papers of other Bergen family and extended family members. Materials in the collection span the years 1639 to 1893, and primarily document Bergen's role as a major civic and community figure in Brooklyn, as well as his family's history. In addition to his work as a farmer and surveyor, Teunis G. Bergen served on the Kings County Board of Supervisors as Supervisor of New Utrecht, NY, and in 1864, he was elected to the United States House of Representatives as a Democrat to the Thirty-ninth Congress. He was also known for his expertise in genealogy and local history, and published several articles and books on these topics. Highlights of the collection include maps, surveys, and map tracings of various Brooklyn locales drafted by Bergen; extensive materials pertaining to Bergen's research and publishing on local history and genealogy; and research materials on Bergen family genealogy.
Scope and Contents note
The Teunis G. Bergen and Bergen family collection spans the period 1639 to 1893 and measures 14 linear feet. The bulk of the collection comprises papers created or compiled by Teunis G. Bergen that document many facets of his professional and personal lives. It includes extensive correspondence written to Bergen, primarily concerning his duties as Supervisor of New Utrecht, as well as letters requesting his expertise in matters of surveying, genealogy, and the history of New Utrecht. A significant portion of the collection documents Bergen's career as a surveyor. These materials include maps, map tracings and surveys drafted by Bergen; drafts of legal documents, including deeds and legal land descriptions; specifications of houses built in Brooklyn and surrounding towns; field notes and calculations; and title searches.
Bergen's activities as a self-trained genealogist and historian are also well-documented. The collection contains a bound, handwritten copy of Bergen's seven-volume A History of New Utrecht, Long Island, as well as research notes and correspondence pertaining to genealogical and local history research conducted by Bergen. Also included in the collection are a variety of Bergen's personal papers, including his childhood schoolbooks, travel logs, financial records, and other ephemera.
The collection also includes papers concerning Teunis G. Bergen's immediate and extended family members, as well as items that document Bergen family history. Materials in the collection document Bergen's father, Garret Bergen; his first cousin once removed, Cornelius Bergen; his wife, Jane C. Bergen; his younger cousin, John C. Bergen; his brother, Peter G. Bergen; and his son, Garret T. Bergen. Of particular interest are a small set of Bergen family land records dated 1696-1700, including maps of Hans Hansen Bergen's land. Also included are correspondence and legal documents between Teunis G. Bergen and members of the Cortelyou, Conover, Cowenhoven, and Wyckoff families, all of whom were related to the Bergens by marriage.
Biographical note on Teunis G. Bergen
Teunis G. Bergen was born in the town of New Utrecht, New York on October 6, 1806, the eldest child of Garret Bergen and his wife Jane (nee Wyckoff). While growing up, he worked on his father's farm in the Gowanus area of Brooklyn and was educated at both the common school of the district and at Erasmus Hall Academy in Flatbush. As a young man, he was trained as a surveyor and subsequently pursued a successful career in this field.
Bergen was also a farmer and an active civic leader. As a member of the 241st regiment of the New York State Militia, he held the ranks of Ensign, Captain, Adjutant, Lieutenant-Colonel, and finally, Colonel. He served on the Kings County Board of Supervisors as the Supervisor of the town of New Utrecht for twenty-three years, 1836-1859, and was Chairman of the Board from 1842 to 1846. Bergen served as a member of the New York State Constitutional Conventions of 1846, 1867, and 1868, and was a delegate to the National Democratic Convention of 1860. In 1864, he was elected to the United States House of Representatives as a Democrat to the Thirty-ninth Congress, an office which he held until 1867.
In addition to his professional and civic activities, Teunis G. Bergen was a self-trained historical researcher and genealogist, as well as a published author. His genealogical interests included not only his own family, but also many other prominent Brooklyn families. His published works include The Register of the Early Settlers and Freeholders of Kings County, NY, from its First Settlement by Europeans, to 1700, with Biographical Notices and Family Genealogies; Genealogy of the Van Brunt Family, 1653-1867; The Bergen Family; or, the Descendents of Hans Hansen Bergen, One of the Early Settlers of New York and Brooklyn, L.I., with Notes on the Genealogy of Some of the Branches of the Cowenhoven, Voorhees, Eldert, Stoothoof, Cortelyou, Stryker, Suydam, Lott, Wyckoff, Barkeloo, Lefferts, Martense, Hubbard, Van Brunt, Vanderbilt, Vanderveer, Van Nuyse, and Other Long Island Families; Genealogy of the Lefferts Family, 1650-1878; and his seven volume A History of New Utrecht, Long Island. Additionally, he contributed frequently to the New York Genealogical and Biographical Record.
Teunis G. Bergen died of pneumonia at his residence in New Utrecht, Long Island at the age of 74, and was interred at Green-Wood Cemetery.
Biographical note on the Bergen family
The Bergen family that settled and proliferated throughout New York and New Jersey beginning in the 17th century is descended from the common ancestor, Hans Hansen Bergen, a native of Bergen, Norway. A ship's carpenter by trade, Bergen moved to Holland as a young man, and subsequently emigrated to the colony of New Amsterdam in 1633. His name appeared in land and church records in different forms, including Hans de Boer, Hans Noorman, Hans Hanszen Van Bergen, Hans Hansen, and Hans Hansen Bergen. It was not until the late 17th or early 18th century that his descendents formally adopted the surname, Bergen.
In 1639, Hans Hansen Bergen married Sara Rapalje, who was mistakenly rumored to have been the first European child born in the colony of New Netherland. They had eight children, among them Michael Hansen Bergen (baptized November 4, 1646), who held civil office for several years and was one of the patentees named in Governor Thomas Dongan's patent of May 13, 1686, which provided the land grant that established the village of Breuklen in the colony of New York. He and his wife, Femmetje Bergen (nee Theunis) had five children.
Michael Hansen Bergen's son, Hans Michielzse Bergen (baptized March 11, 1689) was a baker who resided near Brooklyn Ferry with his wife, Rachel (nee Bensing or Benson). They had seven children, among them Tunis Bergen (baptized October 15, 1730), who held civil and military office in Brooklyn. Tunis and his wife, Johanna (nee Stoothoff) had nine children, including their son, Garret Bergen.
Garret Bergen (born January 11, 1772) held civil and church office in Brooklyn, and was married to Jane Wyckoff on January 6, 1806. Together they had eleven children, including their first born, Teunis G. Bergen, who was born on October 6, 1806.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged in two manuscript groups. Group 1 is organized into six series:
Missing Title
Correspondence (alphabetical)
Financial Records
Genealogical Research
History of New Utrecht
Personal Papers
Surveying Records
Group 2 is organized into two series:
Missing Title
Bergen Family Papers
Bergen Extended Family Papers
Within each group, series and folders are arranged alphabetically.
Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |v Maps; Conveyancing |z New York (State); Correspondence; Deeds |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Genealogy -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Land titles; Legislators |z United States; Maps; New Utrecht (New York, N.Y.); New Utrecht (New York, N.Y.) |x History; Photographs; Surveying; Bergen family; Bergen, Teunis G.; Democratic Party (New York, N.Y.); Democratic Party (N.Y.). State Convention; Kings County (N.Y.). Board of Supervisors; New Utrecht Reformed Church (New York, N.Y.); New York (State). Legislature; United States. Congress. House
- Group 1: Teunis G. Bergen papers
  - Series 1: Correspondence (alphabetical), 1828-1888; 2 Linear Feet in 5 boxes
    Scope and Contents
    Correspondence (alphabetical) consists of correspondence written to Teunis G. Bergen that was culled from his office records. Documents in this series are arranged alphabetically according to the name of the correspondent. The bulk of the correspondence concerns Bergen's duties as Supervisor of New Utrecht. In addition, there are letters requesting his expertise in matters of genealogy, history, and surveying, as well as invitations to civic, social, and political events.
    - Correspondence - A, 1845-1881 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence - A, 1848-1882 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence - B, 1830-1888 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence - B, 1835-1866 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence - B, 1863-1881 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence - C, 1835-1866 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence - C, 1841-1879 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence - C, 1867-1881 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence - D, 1834-1866 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence - D, 1824-1866 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence - D, 1867-1881 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence - E, 1842-1881 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence - E, 1846-1875 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence - F, 1851-1881 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence - F, 1864-1881 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence - G, 1832-1881 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence - G, 1837-1881 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence - H, 1843-1866 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence - H, 1858-1881 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence - H, 1867-1881 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence - I, 1852-1881 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence - I, 1857-1880 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence - J, 1832-1878 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence - J, 1851-1881 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence - K, 1842-1882 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence - K, 1842-1882 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence - L, 1836-1881 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence - L, 1836-1881 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence - L, 1837-1865 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence - L, 1866-1880 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence - M, 1828-1887 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence - M, 1836-1865 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence - M, 1866-1870, 1876 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence - M, 1871-1881 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence - N, 1849-1881 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence - N, 1852-1882 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence - O, 1802-1883 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence - P, 1839-1886 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence - Q, 1864-1878 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence - R, 1848-1882 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence - S, 1830-1888 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence - S, 1832-1867 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence - S, 1868-1882 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence - T, 1841-1879 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence - U, 1837-1882 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence - V, 1831-1887 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence - W, 1852-1883 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence - Y, 1865-1884 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence - Z, 1843-1876 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Series 2: Financial records, 1820-1880; 3 Linear Feet in 7 boxes.
    Financial records comprises documents pertaining to Bergen's personal finances, including account ledgers; bank books; bank, tax and business receipts; property deeds; expenditure books; bank checks; etc.
    - Account as Commissioner on Aqueduct lands, 1856 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Account books, ca. 1856-1880 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Account ledger & journal, 1820 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Account ledger, 1827-1874 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Account ledger, 1827-1874 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Account with hired hands, 1829-1874 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Accounts with Baldwin, circa 1830-1881 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Accounts with Chauncey, D&M, circa 1840-1880 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Accounts with Folk, J.M., circa 1840-1880 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Accounts with McDougal, Isaac, circa 1840-1880 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Accounts - Miscellaneous, circa 1840-1880 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Bank books, 1833-1874 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Bank checks, circa 1840-1880 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Bank checks, circa 1840-1880 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Bay Ridge Fire Department - Ledger of Dues, 1861-1893 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Blotters No. II & III, circa 1840-1880 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Board of Supervisors, 1846-1858 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Cash Books (A-D), 1827-1853 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Cash books (E), 1853-1880 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Day books (A-C), 1827-1880 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Deed - Gravesend, 1710 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Deeds & Agreements - New Utrecht, 1815-1827 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Expenditures (A-B), 1827 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Expenditures (C-D), 1843-1856 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Expenditures (E-F), 1856-1880 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Expense books, 1824-1837; 1850-1862 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Journal on horticulture, 1823-1828 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Journals, 1867-1873 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Market Produce books, circa 1850's (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Memorandum books, 1856-1858 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1830-1881 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous/receipts, 1860-1881 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Receipts, 1827-1838 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Receipts, 1838-1846 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Receipts, 1847-1853 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Receipts, 1853-1855 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Receipts, 1860-1863 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Receipts, 1863-1868 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Receipts, 1865-1871 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Receipts, 1872-1873 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Receipts, 1874-1875 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Receipts, 1873-1880 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Surveys, 1846-1857 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Series 3: Genealogical research, 1858-1880; 1 Linear Feet in 2 boxes.
    Genealogical research primarily consists of the research materials compiled by Bergen to write his book, The Bergen Family: Or the Descendents of Hans Hansen Bergen, One of the Early Settlers of New York and Brooklyn, L.I. Correspondence in this collection consists of responses of Bergen extended family members concerning birth, marriage, and death dates. The miscellaneous folders contain research materials from a variety of sources and includes what appear to be drafts of his book. The folders titled with geographic place names consist of research materials pertaining to branches of the Bergen family in relation to the areas in which they settled. Also included are items related to the genealogy of other prominent Brooklyn families. The Coats of Arms folder contains coats of arms of the Schenck, Van der Veer, Lott, Cowenhoven, Voorhies, and Van Duyn families. The Schenck family correspondence consists of letters to Bergen from members of the Schenck family of Brooklyn requesting information on their family's genealogy. These letters highlight Bergen's role in his community as an expert on local history and genealogy.
    - Coat of Arms, Date unknown (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Colonial manuscripts (handwritten copies), circa 1830-1881 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1858-1869 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1870-1880 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous research, circa 1830-1881 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous research, circa 1830-1881 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous research, circa 1830-1881 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Regional - Brooklyn, 1860-1881 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Regional - Midwestern United States, 1871-1873 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Regional - New Jersey, circa 1830-1881 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Regional - New Jersey, circa 1830-1881 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Regional - New York City, 1859, 1862, 1872 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Regional - Nova Scotia, Canada, 1873 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Regional - Queens and Long Island (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Regional - Staten Island (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Regional - Upstate New York, nd (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Signatures of Bergen ancestors and family members, 1639-1820 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Series 4: History of New Utrecht, 1650-1881; 1.6 Linear Feet in 4 boxes.
    History of New Utrecht is organized into three subseries. Bound volumes consists of bound copies of Teunis G. Bergen's seven-volume work, A History of New Utrecht, Long Island, Chapter drafts consists of handwritten drafts of the book's chapters, and New Utrecht records comprises records concerning the history of New Utrecht. Included in the records are the abstracts of land deeds of New Utrecht residents dating back to the 17th century; brief narrative histories of the Methodist, Episcopal, and Dutch Reformed churches of New Utrecht; a list of constables of New Utrecht dating back to the 17th century; local election records from 1849 to 1858; translations of Dutch records from the town of New Utrecht by Bergen, including issues of the Brooklyn Eagle in which some translations were published; records of various New Utrecht civic offices; etc.
    - Subseries 1: Bound volumes, circa 19th century
      - Volume 1: Chapters 1-4, circa 1830-1881 (Box 14, Folder 8)
      - Volume 2: Chapters 5-8, 1673-1783 (Box 14, Folder 9)
      - Volume 3: Chapters 9-13, 1783-1857 (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Volume 4: Chapters 14-18, circa 1830-1881 (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - Volume 5: Chapters 19-20; appendices 1 & 2, circa 1830-1881 (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - Volume 6: Appendices 3-7, circa 1830-1881 (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - Volume 7: Index, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Subseries 2: Chapter drafts, circa 1830-1881
      - Chapter 1, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Chapter 2, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - Chapter 3, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Chapter 4, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - Chapter 5, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - Chapter 6, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - Chapter 7, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - Chapter 8, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 9)
      - Chapter 9, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Chapter 10, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Chapter 11, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 12)
      - Chapter 12, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 13)
      - Chapter 13, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 14)
      - Chapter 14, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 15)
      - Chapter 15, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 16)
      - Chapter 16, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 17)
      - Appendix 2, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 18)
      - Appendix 3, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 19)
      - Appendix 4, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 19)
      - Appendix 5, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 20)
      - Appendix 7, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 21)
      - Appendix 8, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 22)
    - Subseries 3: New Utrecht records, 1650-1865
      - Board of Health, 1856 (Box 16, Folder 23)
      - Boundary dispute with Gravesend, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 24)
      - Churches: Episcopal, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 25)
      - Churches: Methodist, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 26)
      - Churches: Reformed Dutch Church, circa 1830-1881 (Box 16, Folder 27)
      - Commissioner of Excise, 1852-1854 (Box 16, Folder 28)
      - Commissioner of Highways, 1843 (Box 16, Folder 29)
      - Common Council meetings, 1838, 1843 (Box 16, Folder 30)
      - Constables, 1684-1719 (Box 16, Folder 31)
      - Copy of report on New Utrecht drainage, 1862 (Box 16, Folder 32)
      - Deeds, 1824-1858 (Box 16, Folder 33)
      - Deeds, abstracts, circa 19th century (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Elections, 1852-1858 (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - Fence Viewers, circa 19th century (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - Elections, polling lists, 1849-1858 (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - Fishing rights, 1841 (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - Genealogies, circa 19th century (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - Justice of the Peace, circa 19th century (Box 17, Folder 7)
      - Military affairs - Lists of officers, 1664-1821 (Box 17, Folder 8)
      - School District #2 - Annual Meeting minutes, 1822-1850 (Box 17, Folder 9)
      - School District #2 - Division of, 1849-1850 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Series 5: Kings County Board of Supervisors, 1836-1863; 1 Linear Feet in 2 boxes.
    Kings County Board of Supervisors comprises documents produced by Bergen during his tenure representing the town of New Utrecht on the Kings County Board of Supervisors. The papers in this series consist of handwritten drafts of laws and ordinances, petitions, requests to the New York State Legislature, and meeting minutes. These documents provide a glimpse into Bergen's role as Supervisor of New Utrecht, as well as some of the political, social, and legal issues of concern during his tenure on the Board.
    - Board of Supervisors, 1837, 1845, 1851, 1857 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Board of Supervisors, 1837, 1845, 1851, 1857 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Board of Supervisors, 1847-1857 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Board of Supervisors, 1850 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Board of Supervisors, circa 1851 (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - Board of Supervisors, 1852 (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - Board of Supervisors, 1853 (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - Board of Supervisors, 1854 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Board of Supervisors, 1855 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Board of Supervisors, 1856 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Board of Supervisors, 1857 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Board of Supervisors, 1858 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Board of Supervisors, 1859 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Board of Supervisors, 1860 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Board of Supervisors, 1862 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Board of Supervisors, 1863 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Board of Supervisors, circa 1836-1859 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Series 6: Personal papers, 1747-1881; 0.2 Linear Feet in one manuscript box
    Personal Papers includes Bergen's childhood school books, legal documents, travel logs, and other ephemera. The correspondence files in this series document many aspects of Bergen's life, including his appointments to the New Utrecht Board of Supervisors, as Commissioner of Records, and to the United States Congress; invitations to various civic functions; requests for land surveying; and correspondence with local residents about farming. The deeds, leases, and mortgages in this series document Bergen's land transactions in New Utrecht. Additionally, the series contains papers pertaining to Bergen's military service, as well as documents concerning the New York State Constitutional Conventions of 1846, 1854, and 1860.
    - Account books, 1864-1865; 1870-1871 (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - American Institute, 1837, 1840-1843 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Appointments, 1834-1880 (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - Bay Ridge property - Abstract of title, nd (Box 18, Folder 14)
    - Belson, Frederick, 1872 (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - Bergen, Teunis G. - Map of land owned in Monmouth County, New jersey, circa 1850-1881 (Box 18, Folder 16)